<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<object name="Altair" type="Star">
	<images>
<image title="Altair">altair_1.png</image>
<image title="">altair__2.jpg</image>
<!--[%IMAGES%]-->
<!-- <image>file.jpg</image> -->
	</images>
	<information>
Altair (Alpha Aquilae, Alpha Aql, α Aquilae, α Aql, Atair) is the brightest star in the constellation Aquila and the twelfth brightest star in the night sky. It is currently in the G-cloud. Altair is an A-type main sequence star with an apparent visual magnitude of 0.77 and is one of the vertices of the Summer Triangle (the other two vertices are marked by Deneb and Vega).
Altair rotates rapidly, with a velocity at the equator of approximately 286 km/s. A study with the Palomar Testbed Interferometer revealed that Altair is not spherical, but is flattened at the poles due to its high rate of rotation. Other interferometric studies with multiple telescopes, operating in the infrared, have imaged and confirmed this phenomenon.

Altair is located 16.7 light-years (5.13 parsecs) from Earth and is one of the closest stars visible to the naked eye. Along with Beta Aquilae and Gamma Aquilae, it forms the well-known line of stars sometimes referred to as the Family of Aquila or Shaft of Aquila.
Altair is a type-A main sequence star with approximately 1.8 times the mass of the Sun and 11 times its luminosity. Altair possesses an extremely rapid rate of rotation; it has a rotational period of approximately 9 hours. For comparison, the equator of the Sun requires a little more than 25 days for a complete rotation. This rapid rotation forces Altair to be oblate; its equatorial diameter is over 20 percent greater than its polar diameter.
Satellite measurements made in 1999 with the Wide Field Infrared Explorer showed that the brightness of Altair fluctuates slightly, varying by less than a thousandth of a magnitude. As a result, it was identified in 2005 as a δ Scuti variable star. Its light curve can be approximated by adding together a number of sine waves, with periods that range between 0.8 and 1.5 hours.
The angular diameter of Altair was measured interferometrically by R. Hanbury Brown and his co-workers at Narrabri Observatory in the 1960s. They found a diameter of 3 milliarcseconds. Although Hanbury Brown et al. realized that Altair would be rotationally flattened, they had insufficient data to experimentally observe its oblateness. Altair was later observed to be flattened by infrared interferometric measurements made by the Palomar Testbed Interferometer in 1999 and 2000. This work was published by G. T. van Belle and his co-authors in 2001.
Theory predicts that, owing to Altair's rapid rotation, its surface gravity and effective temperature should be lower at the equator, making the equator less luminous than the poles. This phenomenon, known as gravity darkening or the von Zeipel effect, was confirmed for Altair by measurements made by the Navy Prototype Optical Interferometer in 2001, and analyzed by Ohishi et al. (2004) and Peterson et al. (2006). Also, A. Domiciano de Souza et al. (2005) verified gravity darkening using the measurements made by the Palomar and Navy interferometers, together with new measurements made by the VINCI instrument at the VLTI.
Altair is one of the few stars for which a direct image has been obtained. In 2006 and 2007, J. D. Monnier and his coworkers produced an image of Altair's surface from 2006 infrared observations made with the MIRC instrument on the CHARA array interferometer; this was the first time the surface of any main-sequence star, apart from the Sun, had been imaged. The false-color image was published in 2007 and can be seen above and to the left; the brighter regions are shown in white and darker regions in blue. In this image, North (the direction towards the North Celestial Pole) is up and East is left, and the white line is the rotational axis of Altair. The black grid shows lines of latitude and longitude in an Altair-centric coordinate system. The von Zeipel effect can be observed in the image, which shows a white spot near the pole and a darker equator. The equatorial radius of the star was estimated to be 2.03 solar radii, and the polar radius 1.63 solar radii—a 25% increase of the stellar radius from pole to equator.
The name Altair has been used since medieval times. It is an abbreviation of the Arabic phrase النسر الطائر, an-nasr aṭ-ṭā’ir (English: The flying eagle). The term Al Nesr Al Tair appeared in Al Achsasi Al Mouakket catalogue, which was translated into Latin as Vultur Volans. This name was applied by the Arabs to the asterism of α, β, and γ Aquilae and probably goes back to the ancient Babylonians and Sumerians, who called α Aquilae the eagle star. The spelling Atair has also been used. Medieval astrolabes of England and Western Europe depicted Altair and Vega as birds.
The Koori people of Victoria also knew Altair as Bunjil, the Wedge-tailed Eagle, and β and γ Aquilae are his two wives the Black Swans. The people of the Murray River knew the star as Totyerguil. The Murray River was formed when Totyerguil the hunter speared Otjout, a giant Murray Cod, who, when wounded, churned a channel across southern Australia before entering the sky as the constellation Delphinus.
In Chinese, the asterism consisting of α, β, and γ Aquilae is known as 河鼓 (Hé Gŭ, English: River Drum). Altair is thus known as 河鼓二 (Hé Gŭ èr, English: the Second Star of the Drum at the River, or more literally, Riverdrum 2). However, it is better known by its other names: 牵牛星 (Qiān Niú Xīng) or 牛郎星 ( Niú Láng Xīng), or in English, Cowherd Star. These names are from the love story of 七夕, Qī Xī, in which Niú Láng and his two children, β and γ Aquilae, are separated from their mother, 織女 (Zhī Nŭ, English: Weaver Girl), the star Vega, by the Milky Way. They are only permitted to meet once a year, when the Milky Way is crossed by a bridge of magpies. The Japanese Tanabata (七夕?) festival, in which Altair is known as Hikoboshi (彦星, , English: 'Cow Herder Star?), is based on this legend.
The people of Micronesia called Altair as Mai-lapa, "big/old breadfruit", while the Māori people called this star as Poutu-te-rangi, "pillar of heaven".
Japan Airlines's Starjet 777-200 JA8983 was named Altair.
In astrology, the star Altair was ill-omened, portending danger from reptiles.
The NASA Constellation Program announced Altair as the name of the Lunar Surface Access Module (LSAM) on December 13, 2007. The Russian-made Beriev Be-200 Altair seaplane is also named after the star.
The 1956 science fiction film Forbidden Planet is set on Altair 4, a presumed planet of the star. Stephen King's 1985 novel "The Tommyknockers" also makes reference to Altair 4, as a desolate wasteland.
The Altair 8800 was one of the first microcomputers intended for home use.
Altair is the name of three United States navy ships: USS Altair (AD-11), USS Altair (AK-257) and USNS Altair (T-AKR-291).
Altair (Altaïr Ibn-La'Ahad) is the name of a recurring protagonist from the video game series Assassin's Creed.
Altair is the name of a 1919 poem by Karle Wilson Baker.
Three of them walk together- She is the fairest of three; And sweet as the heavenly weather She maketh the heart of me!"
The A-type main sequence star has the multiple star designation WDS 19508+0852A and has three visual companion stars, WDS 19508+0852B, C, and D. Component B is not physically close to A but merely appears close to it in the sky.
Coordinates: 19h 50m 46.9990s, +08° 52′ 05.959″

<!-- Plain text -->
	</information>
	<characteristics>
<characteristic name="Constellation">Aquila</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Right ascension">19h 50m 46.99855s</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Declination">+08° 52′ 05.9563″</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Apparent magnitude (V)">0.77</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Spectral type">A7 V</characteristic>
<characteristic name="U−B color index">+0.08</characteristic>
<characteristic name="B−V color index">+0.22</characteristic>
<characteristic name="V−R color index">0.0</characteristic>
<characteristic name="R−I color index">+0.14</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Variable type">Delta Scuti</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Radial velocity (Rv)">−26.1 ± 0.9 km/s</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Proper motion (μ)">RA: +536.23 mas/yr, Dec.: +385.29 mas/yr</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Parallax (π)">194.95 ± 0.57mas</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Distance">16.73 ± 0.05 ly (5.13 ± 0.01 pc)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Absolute magnitude (MV)">2.21</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Mass">1.79 M☉</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Radius">1.63 to 2.03 R☉</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Luminosity">10.6 L☉</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Surface gravity (log g)">4.29 cgs</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Temperature">6,900 to 8,500 K</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Metallicity [Fe/H]">−0.2 dex</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Rotation">8.9 hours</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Rotational velocity (v sin i)">240 km/s</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Age">&lt; 1 Gyr</characteristic>

<!-- <characteristic name="name">value</characteristic> -->
	</characteristics>
	<link title="Get more info about Altair in Wikipedia" icon="wiki.png">http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altair</link>
</object>
