<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<object name="Caelum" type="Constellation">
	<images>
<image title="Caelum">caelum_1.png</image>
<image title="Caelum depicted in Urania's Mirror">caelum__2.jpg</image>
<image title="Image of the constellation Caelum, showing the pattern of its stars as seen in the night sky">caelum__3.jpg</image>
<image title="An image of the Seyfert galaxy HE0450-2958, showing the active nucleus">caelum__4.jpg</image>
<!--[%IMAGES%]-->
<!-- <image>file.jpg</image> -->
	</images>
	<information>
Caelum /ˈsiːləm/ is a faint constellation in the southern sky, introduced in the 1750s by Nicolas Louis de Lacaille. Its name means "the chisel" in Latin, and it was formerly known as Caelum Scalptorium, "the engraver's chisel". It is the eighth smallest constellation, and subtends a solid angle of around 0.038 steradians, just less than that of Corona Australis.
Due to its small size and location away from the plane of the Milky Way, Caelum is a rather barren constellation, with few objects of interest. The constellation's brightest star, Alpha Caeli, is only of magnitude 4.45, and only one other star (Gamma1 Caeli) is brighter than magnitude 5. Other notable objects in Caelum are RR Caeli, a binary star with one planet approximately 20.13 parsecs (65.7 ly) away; X Caeli, a Delta Scuti variable that forms an optical double with Gamma1 Caeli; and HE0450-2958, a Seyfert galaxy that at first appeared as just a jet with no host galaxy visible.

Caelum was first introduced in the eighteenth century by Nicolas Louis de Lacaille, a French astronomer who also introduced thirteen other southern constellations at the same time. While the constellation was originally romanized to Caelum Scalptorium (The Engraver's Chisel), Francis Baily shortened this name to Caelum after suggestion by John Herschel. In Lacaille's original chart, the constellation was recognized as burin and an échoppe, although it has come to be recognized simply as a chisel.Johann Elert Bode depicted the name as plural, Caela Scalptoris, but this did not stick.
Caelum is bordered by Dorado and Pictor to the south, Horologium and Eridanus to the east, Lepus to the north, and Columba to the west. Covering 125 square degrees, it ranks 81st of the 88 constellations in size. It appears prominently in the southern sky during the Southern Hemisphere's summer. Its main asterism consists of 4 stars. The constellation's boundaries, as set by Eugène Delporte in 1930, are defined by a 12-sided polygon. In the equatorial coordinate system, the right ascension coordinates of these borders lie between 04h 19.5m and 05h 05.1m, while the declination coordinates are between −27.02° and −48.74°. The International Astronomical Union (IAU) adopted the three-letter abbreviation "Cae" for the constellation in 1922.
Caelum is a faint constellation, having no star brighter than fourth magnitude and only two brighter than fifth magnitude. Lacaille gave six stars Bayer designations, labeling them Alpha to Zeta in 1756, but omitted Epsilon and designated two nearby stars as Gamma. Bode extended the designations to Rho for other stars but all have mostly fallen out of use. Caelum is too far south for any of its stars to bear Flamsteed designations.
The brightest star, Alpha Caeli, is a double star, containing an F-type main-sequence star of magnitude 4.45 and a red dwarf of magnitude 12.5, 20.17 parsecs (65.8 ly) from Earth.Beta Caeli, another F-type star of magnitude 5.05, is slightly further at a distance of 28.67 parsecs (93.5 ly) from Earth. Unlike Alpha, Beta Caeli is a subgiant star, slightly evolved from the main sequence.Delta Caeli, also of magnitude 5.05, is a B-type subgiant and is much farther from earth, at 216 parsecs (700 ly).
Gamma1 Caeli is a double star with a red giant primary of magnitude 4.58 and a secondary of magnitude 8.1. The primary is 55.59 parsecs (181.3 ly) from Earth. The two components are difficult to resolve with small amateur telescopes because of their difference in visual magnitude and their close separation. This star system forms an optical double with the unrelated X Caeli (Gamma2 Caeli), a Delta Scuti variable located 98.33 parsecs (320.7 ly) from Earth. These are a class of short-period (six hours at most) pulsating stars that have been used as standard candles and as subjects to study astroseismology. The only other variable star in Caelum visible to the naked eye is RV Caeli, a pulsating red giant of spectral type M1III, which varies between magnitudes 6.44 and 6.56.
Three other stars in Caelum are still occasionally referred to by their Bayer designations, although they are only on the edge of naked-eye visibility. Nu Caeli is another double star, containing a white giant of magnitude 6.07 and a star of magnitude 10.66 with unknown spectral type. The system is approximately 52.55 parsecs (171.4 ly) away.Lambda Caeli, at magnitude 6.24, is much redder and farther away, being a red giant around 227 parsecs (740 ly) from Earth.Zeta Caeli is even fainter, being only of magnitude 6.36. This star, located 132 parsecs (430 ly) away, is a K-type subgiant of spectral type K1. The other twelve naked-eye stars in Caelum are not referred to by Bode's Bayer designations anymore, including RV Caeli.
One of the nearest stars in Caelum is the eclipsing binary star RR Caeli, at a distance of 20.13 parsecs (65.7 ly). This star system consists of a dim red dwarf in orbit around a white dwarf. Despite its closeness to the Earth, the system's apparent magnitude is only 14.40 due to the faintness of its components, and thus cannot be easily seen with amateur equipment. In 2012, the system was found to contain a giant planet, and there is evidence for a second substellar body. The system is a post-common-envelope binary, and the red dwarf star is transferring material onto the white dwarf. The system is losing angular momentum over time, which will eventually cause mass transfer from the red dwarf to the white dwarf. In approximately 9–20 billion years, this will cause the system to become a cataclysmic variable.
Due to its small size and location away from the plane of the Milky Way, Caelum is rather devoid of deep-sky objects, and contains no Messier objects. Two galaxies somewhat of note are NGC 1571, a lenticular galaxy, and NGC 1679, a barred spiral galaxy with a spectrum containing emission lines. The only deep-sky object in Caelum to receive much attention is HE0450-2958, an unusual Seyfert galaxy. Originally, the jet's host galaxy proved elusive to find, and this jet appeared to be emanating from nothing. Although it has been suggested that the object is an ejected supermassive black hole, the host is now agreed to be a small galaxy that is difficult to see due to light from the jet and a nearby starburst galaxy.
Coordinates: 05h 00m 00s, −40° 00′ 00″

<!-- Plain text -->
	</information>
	<characteristics>
<characteristic name="Abbreviation">Cae</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Genitive">Caeli</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Pronunciation">/ˈsiːləm/, genitive /ˈsiːlaɪ/</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Symbolism">the chisel</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Right ascension">04h 19.5m to 05h 05.1m</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Declination">−27.02° to −48.74°</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Family">La Caille</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Quadrant">SQ1</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Area">125 sq. deg. (81st)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Main stars">4</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bayer/Flamsteed stars">8</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars with planets">1</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars brighter than 3.00m">0</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars within 10.00 pc (32.62 ly)">0</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Brightest star">α Cae (4.45m)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Nearest star">HD 30876 (57.87 ly, 17.75 pc)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Messier objects">0</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Meteor showers">None</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bordering constellations">Columba, Lepus, Eridanus, Horologium, Dorado, Pictor</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Visibility">Visible at latitudes between +40° and −90°. Best visible at 21:00 (9 p.m.) during the month of January.</characteristic>

<!-- <characteristic name="name">value</characteristic> -->
	</characteristics>
	<link title="Get more info about Caelum in Wikipedia" icon="wiki.png">http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caelum</link>
</object>
