<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<object name="Canes Venatici" type="Constellation">
	<images>
<image title="Canes Venatici">canes venatici_1.png</image>
<image title="">canes_venatici__2.gif</image>
<image title="">canes_venatici__3.jpg</image>
<image title="">canes_venatici__4.jpg</image>
<image title="">canes_venatici__5.jpg</image>
<!--[%IMAGES%]-->
<!-- <image>file.jpg</image> -->
	</images>
	<information>
Canes Venatici /ˈkeɪniːz vɨˈnætɨsaɪ/ is one of the 88 official modern constellations. It is a small northern constellation that was created by Johannes Hevelius in the 17th century. Its name is Latin for "hunting dogs", and the constellation is often depicted in illustrations as representing the dogs of Boötes the Herdsman, a neighboring constellation.

The stars of Canes Venatici are not bright. In classical times, they were included by Ptolemy within the constellation Ursa Major in his star catalogue. α CVn was Ptolemy's "28th of Ursa Major", and β CVn was his "29th of Ursa Major".
In the medieval times, the identification of these stars with the dogs of Boötes arose through a mistranslation. Some of Boötes' stars were traditionally described as representing the club (Greek, Κολλοροβος) of Boötes. When the Greek astronomer Ptolemy's Almagest was translated from Greek to Arabic, the translator Johannitius (following Alberuni) did not know the Greek word and rendered it as the nearest-looking Arabic word, writing العصى ذات الكلاب in ordinary unvowelled Arabic text "al-`aşā dhāt al-kullāb", which means "the spearshaft having a hook". When the Arabic text was translated into Latin, the translator Gerard of Cremona (probably in Spain) mistook the Arabic word كلاب for kilāb (the plural of كلب kalb), meaning "dogs", writing hastile habens canes ("spearshaft having dogs"). In 1533, the German astronomer Peter Apian depicted Boötes as having two dogs with him.
These spurious dogs floated about the astronomical literature until Hevelius decided to specify their presence in the sky by making them a separate constellation in 1687. Hevelius chose the name Asterion (from the Greek 'αστέριον, meaning the "little star", the diminutive of 'αστηρ the "star", or adjective meaning "starry") for the northern dog and Chara (from the Greek χαρά, meaning "joy") for the southern dog, as Canes Venatici, the Hunting Dogs, in his star atlas. In his star catalogue, the Czech astronomer Becvar assigned Asterion to β CVn and Chara to α CVn.
Canes Venatici is bordered by Ursa Major to the north and west, Coma Berenices to the south, and Bootes to the east. The three-letter abbreviation for the constellation, as adopted by the International Astronomical Union in 1922, is 'CVn'. The official constellation boundaries, as set by Eugène Delporte in 1930, are defined by a polygon of 14 sides. In the equatorial coordinate system, the right ascension coordinates of these borders lie between 12h 06.2m and 14h 07.3m, while the declination coordinates are between +27.84° and +52.36°. Covering 465 square degrees, it ranks 38th of the 88 constellations in size.
Canes Venatici contains no bright stars, α and β CVn being only of 3rd and 4th magnitude respectively. Flamsteed catalogued 25 stars in the constellation, labelling them 1 to 25 Canum Venaticorum, however 1 turned out to be in Ursa Major, 13 was in Coma Berenices and 22 did not exist.
Canes Venatici contains five Messier objects, including four galaxies. One of the more significant galaxies in Canes Venatici is the Whirlpool Galaxy (M51, NGC 5194) and NGC 5195, a small barred spiral galaxy that is seen face on. This was the first galaxy recognised as having a spiral structure, this structure being first observed by Lord Rosse in 1845. It is a face-on spiral galaxy 37 million light-years from Earth. Widely considered to be one of the most beautiful galaxies visible, M51 has many star-forming regions and nebulae in its arms, coloring them pink and blue in contrast to the older yellow core. M51 has a smaller companion, NGC 5195, that has very few star-forming regions and thus appears yellow. It is passing behind M51 and may be the cause of the larger galaxy's prodigious star formation.
Other notable spiral galaxies in Canes Venatici are the Sunflower Galaxy (M63, NGC 5055), M94 (NGC 4736), and M106 (NGC 4258). M63, the Sunflower Galaxy, was named for its appearance in large amateur telescopes. It is a spiral galaxy with an integrated magnitude of 9.0. M94 is a small face-on spiral galaxy with an approximate magnitude of 8.0, about 15 million light-years from Earth.NGC 4631 is a barred spiral galaxy, which is one of the largest and brightest edge-on galaxies in the sky.
M3 (NGC 5272) is a globular cluster 32,000 light-years from Earth. It is 18' in diameter, and at magnitude 6.3 is bright enough to be seen with binoculars. It can even be seen with the naked eye under particularly dark skies.
M94, also classified as NGC 4736, is a face-on spiral galaxy 15 million light-years from Earth. It has very tight spiral arms and a bright core. The outskirts of the galaxy are incredibly luminous in the ultraviolet because of a ring of new stars surrounding the core, 7,000 light-years in diameter. Though astronomers are not sure what has caused this ring of new stars, some hypothesize that it is from shock waves caused by a bar that is thus far invisible.
Coordinates: 13h 00m 00s, +40° 00′ 00″

<!-- Plain text -->
	</information>
	<characteristics>
<characteristic name="Abbreviation">CVn</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Genitive">Canum Venaticorum</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Pronunciation">/ˈkeɪniːz vɨˈnætɨsaɪ/ Cánes Venátici, genitive /ˈkeɪnəm vɨnætɨˈkɒrəm/</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Symbolism">the Hunting Dogs</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Right ascension">12h 06.2m to 14h 07.3m</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Declination">+27.84° to +52.36°</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Family">Ursa Major</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Quadrant">NQ3</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Area">465 sq. deg. (38th)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Main stars">2</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bayer/Flamsteed stars">21</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars with planets">4</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars brighter than 3.00m">1</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars within 10.00 pc (32.62 ly)">2</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Brightest star">Cor Caroli (α CVn) (2.90m)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Nearest star">DG CVn (25.89 ly, 7.94 pc)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Messier objects">5</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Meteor showers">Canes Venaticids</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bordering constellations">Ursa Major, Boötes, Coma Berenices</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Visibility">Visible at latitudes between +90° and −40°. Best visible at 21:00 (9 p.m.) during the month of May.</characteristic>

<!-- <characteristic name="name">value</characteristic> -->
	</characteristics>
	<link title="Get more info about Canes Venatici in Wikipedia" icon="wiki.png">http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canes_Venatici</link>
</object>
