<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<object name="Messier 85" type="Galaxies">
	<images>
		<image title="">m85_1.jpg</image>
	</images>
	<information>
Messier 85 (also known as M85 or NGC 4382 or PGC 40515 or ISD 0135852) is a lenticular galaxy, or elliptical galaxy for other authors,[3] in the Coma Berenices constellation. It is 60 million light years away, and it is estimated to be 125,000 light years across.
It was discovered by Pierre Méchain in 1781. It is the northernmost outlier of the Virgo cluster discovered as of 2004
It's extremely poor in neutral hydrogen and has a very complex outer structure with shells and ripples that are thought to have been caused by a merger with another galaxy that took place between 4 and 7 billion years ago, as well as a relatively young (less than 3 billion years old) stellar population on its centermost region, some of it in a ring, that may have been created by a late starburst.
Messier 85 may have a central supermassive black hole with a mass of 100 million solar masses.
The type I supernova, 1960R was discovered in M85 on December 20, 1960 and reached an apparent magnitude of 11.7.
This galaxy has also been the host of the first luminous red nova identified as such, M85 OT2006-1. It was discovered on January 7 of 2006 and took place on the outskirts of this galaxy.
M85 is interacting with the nearby spiral galaxy NGC 4394, and a small elliptical galaxy called MCG 3-32-38.
	</information>
	<characteristics>
		<characteristic name="Constellation">Coma Berenices</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Right ascension">12h 25m 24.0s</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Declination">+18° 11′ 28″</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Redshift">729 ± 2 km/s</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Distance">60 ± 4 Mly (18.5 ± 1.2 Mpc)</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Type">SA(s)0+ pec[1]/E2</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Apparent dimensions (V)">7′.1 × 5′.5</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Apparent magnitude (V)">10.0</characteristic>
		<characteristic name="Other designations">NGC 4382, UGC 7508, PGC 40515</characteristic>
	</characteristics>
	<link title="Get more info about Messier 85 in Wikipedia" icon="wiki.png">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messier_85</link>
</object>
