<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<object name="Puppis" type="Constellation">
	<images>
<image title="Puppis">puppis_1.png</image>
<image title="">puppis__2.jpg</image>
<image title="">puppis__3.jpg</image>
<!--[%IMAGES%]-->
<!-- <image>file.jpg</image> -->
	</images>
	<information>
Puppis /ˈpʌpɨs/ is a constellation in the southern sky. Puppis, the Poop Deck, was originally part of an over-large constellation, the ship of "Jason and the Argonauts", Argo Navis, which centuries after its initial description, was divided into three parts, the other two being Carina (the keel and hull), and Vela (the sails of the ship). Puppis is the largest of the three constellations in square degrees. It is one of the 88 modern constellations recognized by the International Astronomical Union.
Argo Navis was sub-divided in 1752 by the French astronomer Nicolas Louis de Lacaille, forming Puppis. Despite the division, Lacaille kept Argo's Bayer designations. Therefore Carina has the α, β and ε, Vela has γ and δ, Puppis has ζ, and so on.
Several extrasolar planet systems have been found around stars in the constellation Puppis, including:
As the Milky Way runs through Puppis, there are a large number of open clusters in the constellation. M46 and M47 are two open clusters in the same binocular field. M47 can be seen with the naked eye under dark skies, and its brightest stars are 6th magnitude. Messier 93 (M93) is another open cluster somewhat to the south. NGC 2451 is a very bright open cluster containing the star c Puppis and the near NGC 2477 is a good target for small telescopes. The star Pi Puppis is the main component of a bright group of stars known as Collinder 135.
M46 is a circular open cluster with an overall magnitude of 6.1 at a distance of approximately 5400 light-years from Earth. The planetary nebula NGC 2438 is superimposed; it is approximately 2900 light-years from Earth. M46 is classified as a Shapley class f and a Trumpler class III 2 m cluster. This means that it is a rich cluster that appears distinct from the star field; however, it is not at its center. The cluster's stars, numbering between 50 and 100, have a moderate range in brightness.
Coordinates: 07h 30m 00s, −30° 00′ 00″

<!-- Plain text -->
	</information>
	<characteristics>
<characteristic name="Abbreviation">Pup</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Genitive">Puppis</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Pronunciation">/ˈpʌpɨs/, genitive the same</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Symbolism">the Poop Deck</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Right ascension">7.5</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Declination">−30</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Family">Heavenly Waters</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Quadrant">SQ2</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Area">673 sq. deg. (20th)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Main stars">9</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bayer/Flamsteed stars">76</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars with planets">6</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars brighter than 3.00m">1</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Stars within 10.00 pc (32.62 ly)">3</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Brightest star">ζ Pup (Naos) (2.25m)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Nearest star">LHS 1989 (19.67 ly, 6.03 pc)</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Messier objects">3</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Meteor showers">Pi Puppids, Zeta Puppids, Puppid-Velids</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Bordering constellations">Monoceros, Pyxis, Vela, Carina, Pictor, Columba, Canis Major, Hydra</characteristic>
<characteristic name="Visibility">Visible at latitudes between +40° and −90°. Best visible at 21:00 (9 p.m.) during the month of February.</characteristic>

<!-- <characteristic name="name">value</characteristic> -->
	</characteristics>
	<link title="Get more info about Puppis in Wikipedia" icon="wiki.png">http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puppis</link>
</object>
